<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A president for young pen-men. Or The letter-writer Containing letters of sundry sortes, with their seuerall answeres. Full of variety, delight, and pleasure, and most necessary for the instruction of those that can write, but haue not the guift of enditing.</title>
            <author>M. R., fl. 1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10301</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20584</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120927</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856120</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856120</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21642</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10301)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21642)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1033:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A president for young pen-men. Or The letter-writer Containing letters of sundry sortes, with their seuerall answeres. Full of variety, delight, and pleasure, and most necessary for the instruction of those that can write, but haue not the guift of enditing.</title>
                  <author>M. R., fl. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld for Robert Wilson, and are to be sold at his shoppe at Grayes Inne Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: M.R.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁴ H² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Letter writing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PRESIDENT FOR YOVNG PEN-MEN. OR THE LETTER-WRITER CONTAINING
LETTERS of ſundry ſortes, with their ſeuerall Anſweres. Full of
Variety, Delight, and Pleaſure, and moſt neceſſary for the
inſtruction of thoſe that can write, but haue not the Guift of
enditing.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>G. Eld,</hi> for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi>
and are to be ſold at his ſhoppe at Grayes Inne Gate. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe latter times euery Ballad-maker will be a Poet, as if
euery Pedler would ſeeme a Merchant, and euery Pettifogger a Lawyer: ſo hee
that can ſcarce endite a Letter, will take vpon him to be a Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: For
my ſelfe, I dare not be ſo ſawcy, as to put ſuch a Title to my Booke;
onely this I haue heere written a few Letters, which, I hope, are ſo
compoſed as will be preſidents for yong pen men, and not diſpleaſing to
elder yeeres: ſuch as they are, I put them out into the world to the
cenſure of all: entreating the beſt to correct what is amiſſe, and the
reſt not to diſcommend that they cannot mend: and reſt as I haue
reaſon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your well-willing friend. M. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, and my moſt worthy eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meed
Kinſman ANTHONY HOBART, of Hales Hall in the County of Norffolke, Eſquire,
all happineſſe on Earth, and the ioyes of Heauen hereafter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N reading of Epiſtles, written in diuers languages, I finde
them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to ſuch Patrones, as could iudge of their worth, and would
accordingly accept them: Some to men of great account; other to men of lower
Titles of honour, but in higher eſteeme of their loue: Now finding great men
ſo buſie in great Matters, that I ſhould haue great adoe with their
patience, in troubling their leiſures from imployment in more ſerious
affaires, and yet knowing my labours, in my Letters, worth the looking on, I
haue bethought me of ſuch a Patron, as in his kindneſſe will vnderſtand
my<pb facs="tcp:21642:5"/>work, and regard my loue; which hauing found in your many
fauours, giue me leaue, with my ſeruice, to preſent my Book to your
Patronage: Each Letter hath his Anſwer; the Subiects are diuers, ſo is the
manner of their enditing: Hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full I know they will not be to any; good they
may do to many, that can aptly make vſe of them: and for your ſelfe, and
perhaps yours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you, it may be no hurt to peruſe them; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, at
your idle leiſure they will ſaue time, and perhaps yeelde you pleaſure in
reading them: but loth to bee tedious in needleſſe Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, I will leaue
them to your kind accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and my loue to your like command: and ſo
reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most louing Kinſman, M. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:5"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Table of all the Letters in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>A Letter of requeſt for a kindneſſe.</item>
               <item>The Anſwer to the ſame.</item>
               <item>A Letter of counſell to a friend in diſtreſſe.</item>
               <item>The Anſwer to the ſame.</item>
               <item>A Letter from a Nephew to his vnckle from the
Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</item>
               <item>The Anſwer to the ſame.</item>
               <item>A Letter of Loue, to a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman of good worth.</item>
               <item>Her Anſwer to the ſame.</item>
               <item>A Letter of kindneſſe from a louing Father, to call horne
an vnthrifty ſonne.</item>
               <item>His Anſwere.</item>
               <item>A Loue letter to a faire Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman.</item>
               <item>Her Anſwer.</item>
               <item>A Letter of diſcontentment to a Gentlewoman of
incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency.</item>
               <item>Her Anſwer.</item>
               <item>A Letter of reprehenſion, of ſuſpected
vnthankfulneſſe.</item>
               <item>His Anſwere.</item>
               <item>A Letter of counſell from a diſcreete Mother, to her
Daughter newly married.</item>
               <item>Her Anſwer.</item>
               <item>A kind letter of a Father to a prodigall ſonne.</item>
               <item>His Anſwer.</item>
               <item>A Letter in a kinde of chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, vppon report of a great
abuſe.</item>
               <item>His Anſwere.</item>
               <item>A Letter to a Kinſman, a yong man towards a Wife.</item>
               <item>His Anſwer.</item>
               <item>A diſcontentiue Letter vpon the deniall of
friendſhip.</item>
               <item>His anſwer.</item>
               <item>A letter from a friend to a fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall conceited
madcap.</item>
               <item>His anſwer.</item>
               <item>A byting Letter to a clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Gentlewoman.</item>
               <item>The Anſwer to the ſame.</item>
               <item>A diſcontentiue Letter of a coy Miſtreſſe.</item>
               <item>Her anſwere.</item>
               <item>A letter written to a friend in time of great
affliction.</item>
               <item>His anſwer.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21642:6"/>A kind of quarrelſome Letter, vpon a frowne of
a friend.</item>
               <item>His Anſwere.</item>
               <item>A Letter to an Vnckle to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a horſe.</item>
               <item>His Anſwere.</item>
               <item>A Letter from an old man, to his adopted Sonne, going from
the Vniuerſity to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile. His anſwer.</item>
               <item>A letter of Counſell not to be preciſe. The
anſwere.</item>
               <item>A letter from a Knight of great place, to a Gentleman to
attend him. His anſwere.</item>
               <item>A Letter to a Knight for the entertainment of a Steward into
his ſeruice.</item>
               <item>A thankfull Letter vpon the tryall of his Seruant.</item>
               <item>A Letter of counſell from a Brother to his Siſter, vpon
her going from the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to the Court.</item>
               <item>Her anſwere.</item>
               <item>A kind letter to a ſcholler go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Vniuerſitie
to a benifice in a Cittie.</item>
               <item>A letter to a worthy Knight beyond the Seas.</item>
               <item>His Anſwer.</item>
               <item>A letter of counſail to a friend going to trauaile.</item>
               <item>His Anſwere.</item>
               <item>A Letter written to a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, by a Gentleman in
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe.</item>
               <item>A pleaſant conceited letter to a friend in the
Country.</item>
               <item>The Anſwer.</item>
               <item>A kind letter to a friend in the Country from the
Citty.</item>
               <item>His Anſwere.</item>
               <item>A melancholy diſcontentiue Letter, vpon a frowne of a
Kinſman.</item>
               <item>A diſcontentiue letter of a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</item>
               <item>The Anſwer.</item>
               <item>A comfortable letter to a kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, vpon the buriall of a
young Sonne.</item>
               <item>The anſwere.</item>
               <item>A Letter to an Hypocrite vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betraying of a Friend.</item>
               <item>His anſwere.</item>
               <item>A Letter of aduice to a friend that was to be married.</item>
               <item>His anſwere.</item>
               <item>A Letter of vnkindneſſe to a Kinſman, vpon a report of
his abuſe. His anſwere.</item>
               <item>A Letter of kindneſſe from a Gentleman to his loue, from
beyond Seas.</item>
               <item>Her anſwere.</item>
               <item>A moſt kind letter from a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to her Seruant of good
worth.</item>
               <item>His anſwer.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:6"/>
            <head>A Letter of Requeſt for a kindneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F you knew my néed, you would not deny me, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
knowing the good you may doe me. Your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe may proue more wit, then loue,
and, my want, more gréeuous, then I hope your good will would me: that
which will hurt you little will help mee much, and what my remembrance ſhall
be of your kindnes, ſhall reſt in my thankfulnes: If proteſtations be not
idle, you will performe the part of a friend, to put your will to your power,
to pleaſure him once that will loue you euer: In Summe, leauing my hopes
comfort to your kinde anſwere, I reſt:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours or not mine owne: <hi>W.
H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Anſwere.</head>
            <p>I Will not deny you, though I cannot help you, in that meaſure
of comfort, that may anſwere your expectation: for, my purſe is not euen
with my Credit, though I will not complaine of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie. Come therefore to me,
and know me, that, Truth hath no Trickes, and I will not falter with a Friend:
as I know my eſtate, I muſt manage my affaires; if I hurt my ſelfe, I can
not help my Friends, but ſince bare words yéeld little comfort, you
ſhall finde better fruits in my affection: I know you are wiſe, and hope to
find you kinde, in being perſwaded of my loue, to be as ready as able to
performe more then I will proteſt: ſo expecting your preſence, in
aſſurance of your patience, till I ſee you, and alwaies, I reſt:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull louing friend: <hi>H.
W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:7"/>
            <head>A Letter of Councell to a Friend in diſtreſſe.</head>
            <p>HOneſt <hi>Will,</hi> I Condole with thée in thy
diſcontentments, though I cannot eaſe thee of thy ſorrowes: but though my
comfort be little, let not my Counſell diſlike thée, to tell
thée what I thinke, that will not be amiſſe for thee to thinke on:
The Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueller muſt not giue ouer, till he come to his iourneys end, and till
the daies worke be done, there is no looking for wages: deepe waters are
dreadfull to them that feare to wet their feet, but, wiſedome will through
though ſhee wade vp to the Chin; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, it is the Euening praiſeth
the Day, and he is only happy that holds out to the end: ſtand therefore to
your tackling: For though your croſſes are greeuous, yet ſurely is your
bleſſing great, in being ſo well able to goe through them: and therefore
fight the good fight, and your conqueſt will be comfortable, and if not
héere, yet in Heauen: ſhortly, God willing, I will ſee thee, and
till then, pray for thee, that thy faith may neuer faile thee: and that I may
find thee in ſuch reſt, that I may ioy in thy Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution: till when, and
alwaies, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, or not mine owne: <hi>D.
S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Anſwere.</head>
            <p>KInde <hi>Robin,</hi> I am ſory you are ſory for me, becauſe
it will doe you more hurt, then me, good: yet am I ſo far comforted in your
Counſell, that if I could be my ſelfe, I ſhould be much benefited by your
inſtructions: but if oppreſſion make the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man mad, beare with the
imperfection of Fooles: and know that when patience is put to her ſtrength,
paſſion, puts Grace to her Triall, I ſpeake not this in diſpaire of
mercy, for God is all-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient as well in Comfort, as Correction: but,
croſſes abroad, and crucifyings at home, vnkindneſſe of kin,
vnfaithfulneſſe of friends, breaches of vowes, delaying of times ſcorns
of beggars,<pb facs="tcp:21642:7"/>and ſcoffes of fooles, with fruſtrating of hopes, in
prayers of faith and teares of repentance, haue almoſt broken my heart, which
onely liues in the Grape to know an end of my griefe: yet will I tarry the
Lords leaſure, and till then reſt full of griefe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, what mine owne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter from a Nephew to his Vncle from the
Vniuerſitie.</head>
            <p>GOod Vnkle you writ vnto me, to know what fruit I haue made of my
ſtudy: To tell you truth, in reading ouer my Alphabet, I found in all the
Croſſe Rowe, the worſt letter was, <hi>O:</hi> eſpecially when
<hi>I,</hi> went before it, and <hi>V:</hi> followed after it: For there
finding that <hi>I o u,</hi> and can not yet come out of your debt, I cannot be
agrieued, that you are di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>contented,
that <hi>I o u,</hi> and can not help it, yet thus much I gaine by my reading,
to finde in my conſcience, the charge of my debts, which I will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge
with all the ſpéed that I am able, and in the meane time entreat my
friends to that patience, that ſhal be nothing to their diſprofit, among
whom holding your loue in no little account, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring you ere long to
héere from me, and in the meane time not vnthankefull for your kindnes:
I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your bounden louing Coſen. <hi>R.
W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Anſwere.</head>
            <p>GOod Coſen in your Alphabet you ſay you find <hi>o,</hi> the
worſt Letter, now, with me it is not ſo: for I finde it rather in
<hi>h:</hi> which I féele not in my Toe, for I am not ſo Rich as to
haue the Gowt, nor in my head, for I thanke God, I haue reaſonable good
health of body, but it is onely at my Heart to thinke of my vnhappineſſe to
haue ſo ill comfort of my kindnes: yet, let mee not write this to trouble
you, your Debt beeing but a Trifle; and therefore knowing your honeſt heart,
I leaue the time, to your beſt abilitie, and in the meane time hoping of your
loue, I<pb facs="tcp:21642:8"/>wiſh you not to hurt your ſelfe to help mee; for though
I am poore I am no begger, and will not be vnkind to them I loue: in which, be
yow aſſured, I will reſt, during life:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing Vnkle: <hi>T. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of Loue to a Gentlewoman of good worth.</head>
            <p>WOrthy Lady, if I could not diſſemble I were a foole, but if I
would I were the more foole, knowing your wiſedome to know craft to be the
greateſt folly, and your vertue to allowe onely Truth, to be the beſt
Elequence: In plaine Truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, giue me leaue, to lay the ſeruice of
my heart, at the feete of your fauour, where if the deſarts of my endeuour
may not bee diſdained, your Honor ſhall not be embaſed, where your vertue
is honored: ſo crauing pardon for my preſumption, in the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie of
affection, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your more willing, then worthy ſeruant: <hi>B.
R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Her Anſwere.</head>
            <p>SIr I haue receiued your Letter, and by the Contents geſſe at
your content: but giue me leaue to tell you that proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are perilous
ſhadowes, and the Diuell neuer deceiues more then when hee comes like an
Angell of light: I ſpeake not this with an ill coniecture to wrong a good
minde, but the world is ſo full of Treaſon, that Truth is crept into a
little Corner: To honour vertue, I cannot denie you, and to deſerue well I
can not diſſwade you, but in the happineſſe of my fauour your hopes may
bee deceiued, though thus farre, I ſubſcribe to your petition, that I will
diſdaine no honorable affection, but wiſh I were a more worthy Miſtris of
ſo worthy a Seruant:<pb facs="tcp:21642:8"/>and ſo in that care of my diſcretion,
that may be no touch to my reputation. I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your well wiſhing friend, <hi>E.
B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of kindnes from a louing father to call home an
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifty Sonne.</head>
            <p>THe Pellican kills her ſelfe, to feeed her young chickins: an
vnkindly brood to bee the death of their breeder: the Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koe kills the Sparrow
that hatcht her: Oh vnnaturall bird to be her death, that gaue her life! and
the little Snakes eat out the belly of their damme ere they come abroad: Oh
moſt hatefull worme to bee of ſo helliſh a nature. Now ſeeing the
ſhame of theſe, wilt thou like a ſhadow follow their ſubſtance? with
thy diſordinate life to bee the death of thy father? I loue thee dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and
wilt thou greiue me deepely? doe not ſo good Sonne: turne the glaſſe of
thy diſgrace, to a courſe of better comfort: Leaue the world and come home
to mee: I will meet thee halfe way with my roabe and with my ring, I will wed
thee to my loue, and the fat Calfe ſhall bee killed to make a feaſt for thy
comming: ſo beſeeching God ſo to bleſſe thee that I may ſee the
fruits of his grace in thee, till I ſee thee or heare from thee, to the Lord
of Heauen I leaue thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy moſt louing father. <hi>W.
R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Anſwere.</head>
            <p>MY déere Father, I moſt humbly thanke you for your kind
Letter; which hath ſo wrought in my loue, as hath almoſt Metamorphoſ'd my
mind from the humor it was in: for ſince that Grace hath opened the eye of my
vnderſtanding, to diſcerne betwixt good and euill, I finde him worſe then
a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill that feareth not God, and a Child to be loathed that loues not his
Father: pardon therefore what is paſt, and feare not<pb facs="tcp:21642:9"/>what is to
come. You inuite me to your houſe, that am worthy to be driuen from your
doore, and will méete me halfe way, that merit baniſhment from your
preſence, and make me a feaſt that deſerues euer to be kept faſting:
but this ſhewes, loue deſcends before it aſcend; God came to Man, ere Man
could come to God; your loue called me to comfort, before I could come to
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it: In ſumme, your kindneſſe hath bound my loue in an
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluable duty, in which I hope ſhortly to ſee you, and till then
euer to pray for you, that all happineſſe may befall you: and ſo humbly
reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your obedient Sonne:</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Loue-letter to a faire Gentlewoman.</head>
            <p>SWéet Creature, if the World did not hold thée
faire. I ſhould thinke my ſelfe blind: and if the wiſe did not admire
thée, I ſhould not ſo much honor thée: but ſince, thy worth
deſerues more honor then I can giue thée, giue me leaue onely to pray
for thée, that no black ſpot of pride may ſtaine the faire white of
thy vertue: but that, continuing in thy goodneſſe, thou mayſt enioy the
fulneſſe of thy happineſſe: and for my ſelfe, that in the deſert of
thy fauour, I may be a Seruant of thy command: in which, more hoping in thy
vertue, then preſuming of my fortune: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy vnworthy Seruant: <hi>B.
T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Her Anſwer.</head>
            <p>KInd Sir; I would be as loath to be the gaze of the Worlds eye, as
the ſubiect of your fiction: and for the honor of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, it ſhould
bee rather in the Heauens then the Earth: for your prayers, I thanke you,
though I hope they are more chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table then neceſſary: and for your
ſeruice, take it not vnkindlie,<pb facs="tcp:21642:9"/>that I wiſh you a more worthy
Miſtris: and ſo intreating you to giue me leaue, to leaue you to your
ſelfe, whom you haue moſt reaſon to make much off; I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Too vnworthy a Miſtris of ſo worthy a Seruant:
<hi>E. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of diſcontentment to a Gentlewoman, ſuſpected of
Incontinency.</head>
            <p>IF you were as wiſe as <hi>Salomon,</hi> yet if you were not
more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, I would not giue a penny for your wit; if you were as rich as
<hi>Craeſus,</hi> yet if you want grace, I would not giue an halfe penny for
your wealth; and if you were as faire as <hi>Venus,</hi> yet, if you want
vertue, I will not giue a point for your painting: Counterfeit modeſty, is
plaine hypocriſie, and to flatter for gaine, is the common courſe of the
world: Babies in gay coats are Childrens ſports, and fooles Idols: For my
ſelfe, I haue knowne you long, and began to loue you, but finding your folly,
I haue with-drawne my affection; and to play faire with you, vpon euen tearmes.
I had rather giue ouer my game with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle loſſe, then haue a bare
ſtake to ſet my reſt vpon: ſo wiſhing you henceforth to make your
beſt match for your aduantage, and not deceiue your ſelfe with hoping after
a fooles fortune, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as little as I can to trouble my thought with your
idle hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors. As I found you, I leaue you: and ſo reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend as I find cauſe: <hi>W.
R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Her Anſwer.</head>
            <p>VVHat you thinke of your ſelfe, I know not, and what your
eſtate is, I care not: it ſéemes you are well read<pb facs="tcp:21642:10"/>in
names, but lack iudgement in applying their natures: they that feare not God
are worſe then the Diuell, and they that want grace are in a pittifull
taking; for vertue, it is ſo rare, that thinke <hi>Venus</hi> better fits
your humour: for your pence, halfe-pence, and points, they are but Pedlers
ware, and therefore I haue nothing to doe with ſuch Chapmen. Hypocriſie
miſtaken, may take Iealouzie in an idle humor, and as good be a painted Baby
as a péeuiſh Bowby: for your gaine, if you be not pleaſed, you may
change your Card or be content with your fortune, and for your franke play you
are ſo freſh a gamſter, that I thinke loſſe of time will be all that
will be gotten by you: and ſo wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to keep your money in your
purſe, play with children for Apples, that you may eat your part of them, if
you looſe: like a white God-ſonne, I wil leaue you to your mothers
bleſſing: and ſo reſt: till I ſée you, which I hope to doe,
neuer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, Aſſe you mine: <hi>M.
T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of reprehenſion of ſuſpected
vnthankfulneſſe.</head>
            <p>COzen how kind you haue found me, you know, and how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull,
I haue found you, I would I did not know: to be ſo long from me, and in your
ſilence to forget me: in the notes of a good nature, I finde no ſuch ill
diſpoſition: but leſt I may wrong you, and my ſelfe, with a falſe
ſuſpition of vnkindneſſe, not knowing the cauſe, that may be
excuſable, I pray you write vnto me by this Bearer: for if the cauſe of
your ſilence haue bin ſicknes, I am ſorie for it, if your Letters haue
béen loſt, or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, we are both wronged, howſoeuer it is
ſomething is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, which I wiſh kindely to be amended: not to
trouble you with a tedious Letter, the Contents perhaps diſcontentiue, till I
heere from you, which I expect preſently, in the nature of a kinſman and
loue of a friend, without great cauſe to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very louing Coſen: <hi>R.
D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:10"/>
            <head>His Anſwere</head>
            <p>MY good Vnkle, how kinde ſo euer I haue found you, I now finde
you contrarie, when in the Conſtruction of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, exprobation,
and vnthankefulneſſe make a hard Choiſe, which is the greater Cut in
vnkindneſſe: you thinke it long, ſince you heard from me, and I heere
from you to ſoone, when, in your writing, I finde you ſo farre from your
ſelfe: for, could I not be my ſelfe, I ſhould forget you: but, if a Carde
come croſſe, ſhall the game be giuen vp? and if there fall out a
miſchance, ſhall it giue ſuſpition of an ill minde? I hope not: well
the cauſe knowne of my ſilence, I leaue ſo the report of this bearer, to
whom I know you will giue truſt: and by whom, I ſend you an other written
long ſince, how miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and returned, being tedious to write, I will
leaue to his deliuerie: ſo hoping, that when you finde where the fault is you
will there lay the repentance, in the true aſſertion of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
kinſman, rather willing to deſerue a good turne, then to heere of it: I
take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very louing Coſen, <hi>N.
W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of Counſell from a diſcreet Mother to her
Daughter, newly married.</head>
            <p>MY good Daughter, thou art now going into the world, and muſt
leaue to be a Child, and learne to be a Mother, and to looke to a family,
rather then to the entertainement of a friend: and yet, both neceſſarie in
their kindes: finde the diſpoſition of thy huſband, and in any wiſe
moue not his impatience: Let thy kindneſſe binde his loue, thy vertue his
comfort, and thy Huſwiferie his commendation: auoide fatling Goſſips, yet
be kinde to thy Neighbours, and no ſtranger to thy kindred, bee gentle to thy
ſeruants, but not ouer-familiar: haue an eye to<pb facs="tcp:21642:11"/>the doore, and a
lock to thy Cheſt: keepe a Bit, for a Beggar, and a Bone, for a Dogge: make
much of the Bée that brings home the honey, and looſe not the Cock
that makes much of his Chickins, take heed abroad of the Kite, and within of
the Rat: pray to God for his bleſſings to all thy proceedings, and haue a
religious care of thy modeſt gouernment, and rather for charitie then
praiſe giue reliefe to the poore: if at any time thou haſt need of any good
I can doe thee, be aſſured while thou haſt a mother, thou haſt a
friend: ſo, hoping in thy kindneſſe, thou wilt take care of my
Counſell, beſéeching God ſo to bleſſe thee that I may euer
haue ioy in thee, with my hearts loue, to his tuition I leaue thee: And ſo
reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy moſt louing Mother. <hi>E.
B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Her Anſwere.</head>
            <p>MY good Mother, you haue paſſed the yéeres of a Child,
and know the Care of a Mother: and therefore, for your kinde aduice for my
cariage I humbly thanke you, and what benefit I will make of your leſſons,
you ſhall finde in the fruit of my obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: I am but newly come into
the world, and God knowes, when I ſhall goe out of it: and am yet ſcarce
warme in my houſe, and therefore hardly know yet how to goe through it: for
my huſbands humor, if he alter not his Nature, I do not doubt, we ſhall
liue as Doues: while care and kindnes ſhall continue content: my ſeruants
ſhall finde me, both a Miſtris and a friend, my Neighbours no ſtranger,
and idle Goſſips no companion: thus in the dutie of loue, with thanks for
motherly care in prayer to the Almightie, to bleſſe me with his Grace, and
to liue no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, then in his loue and yours, I take my leaue: for this time,
but reſt during life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt louing Daughter,
<hi>E.W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:11"/>
            <head>A kinde Letter of a Father, to a Prodigall Sonne.</head>
            <p>MY Sonne, for thée to ſpend careleſly, that which with
great care I haue gotten, may be as much thy diſgrace, as my griefe: when I
would doe thée good, and ſhall not be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, and thou
ſhalt doe thy ſelfe hurt, when I cannot help it: I can be content to
encreaſe thy exhibition, but to maintaine Riotouſnes, is to Nurſe
iniquitie: yet let me not be bitter in my reprehenſion: but, let my kindnes
be thy correction: Let mee know thy wants, and I will ſupply them: but let
them not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed my abilitie, leaſt I be ſhort to relieue them: I know thou
haſt wit to conſider of my writing, and I hope thou haſt Grace to make
vſe of thy vnderſtanding: and therefore, to be briefe, in the loue of a
Father, I leaue thee to thy heauenly Father: who, I hope, will ſo bleſſe
thee, that, I ſhall haue ioy in thee: ſo, hoping to heare from thee, and
that good of thee, that may make me glad to know it, in thee: till I ſee
thee, and alwaies: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy louing Father: <hi>R. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>MY good Father, your reprehenſion was to kind for ſo
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious a Sonne, and yet the mildnes of your Counſell, hath ſo wrought
in my loue, that the limits of your direction, ſhall be the paſſage of my
life: and ſuch ſhall be henceforth my care of your comfort, as I ſhall
rather, wiſh my graue, then your griefe: I haue called my wits to account,
and in the expence of Prodigalitie, I finde ſo poore a reckoning, that the
ſumme will bee all in miſerie, where ſorrow hath little comfort: I haue
cut my finger, but not wounded my hand, and a little Salue will make all hole:
my wants are not great, but I wiſh rather to want life, then grace to be
thankefull to God, for his goodnes, and to you for your kindneſſe: ſo, in
the due and true obedience of loue, praying for your health, and hearts eaſe:
I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt louing Sonne: <hi>H.
P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:12"/>
            <head>A Letter in a kinde of Challenge, vpon report of a great
abuſe.</head>
            <p>HOw you haue wrongd me you know, but how you will right mee, I
know not: Patience is a vertue, alſo would I quit a villanie in a true kinde:
good wordes will hardly excuſe ill actions: I know you are cunning, I wiſh
you were honeſt: to abuſe any man, is but the Badge of an ill minde, but to
wrong a friend is a proofe of a vile Nature: which how I can diſgeſt you
ſhall finde as it fals out: and leaſt ſufferance may be thought
Cowardice, let this ſuffice, giue mee a ſpeedie ſatiſfaction, or to
haue your wages for your good worke: and ſo till I heare from you, to a
better end then I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours as I haue: <hi>S. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>IF your rage were not aboue your reaſon, I ſhould thinke to
ſatiſfie your diſcretion; but let me tell you, the truth, in being to
credulous vpon report, you may wrong your ſelfe and your friend: I ſpeake
not this in feare of your threates, but to cleere my conſcience of a falſe
accuſation: I know no wrong I haue done you, and how I am reſolued to right
you, when occaſion ſhall ſerue you ſhal, finde what is in me: if you
will be at quiet with your ſelfe, your friends will not trouble you, and he
that is your ſeruant pay him his ſtipend: for mine own part, I am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
in your debt, but for a few foule words: which I will bury in obliuion, except
neceſſitie of occaſion, wherein yet I will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a methode not to
paſſe the courſe of good maner: ſo hoping ere long to find you in a
better humor: I reſt, as I haue reaſon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, as you mine. <hi>I. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:12"/>
            <head>A Letter to a Kinſman, a young man towards a Wife.</head>
            <p>GOod Coſen, I heare you are in loue, I wiſh it with all the
world: and that your affection is forcible, I hope it is in vertue, but that it
is with a woman, which makes mee to feare your weakeneſſe: either in ſome
touch of her vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or your owne: I ſpeake not this to
diſſwade you from marriage, for the courſe is honourable: but if there be
a croſſe to content, it may proue diſcomfortable: what euer it bee, I
wiſh it, to the beſt, but let mee entreat you, not to conceale from my
Loue, vpon what ground you haue builded the houſe of your hopes comfort, that
if I like the platforme, I may the better pray for your proſperitie, and in
the hope of your good huſbandry, bee glad of your thrift: I know not your
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, but what euer be your ſubiect, make not your ſelfe an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect: in
briefe, acquaint me, I pray you, with your procéedings, that when you
draw your deeds my hand may doe you no hurt: ſo wiſhing you firſt to
ſerue God, and then to looke to your ſelfe, and to know <hi>Diana,</hi>
before you bee to buſie with <hi>Cupid,</hi> in the heartie loue of a true
Kinſman, till I heere from thee, and alwaies: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt louing Vnkle. <hi>T.
R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>MY good Vnkle, I thanke you for your kinde Letter, and touching
the Contents, I hope my Anſwere ſhall not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content you, that I am in
Loue, I doe not deny it, but with all the world I wil not confeſſe it, for
the Reprobates are out of the Rule of Charitie: that my affection is of force,
I grant it, for ſo had I rather haue it, then fantaſtick, and with a woman
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, for ſhall wee abandon their loue, by whom wee haue<pb facs="tcp:21642:13"/>our breeding to life? I know it is not your meaning: for my
weakeneſſe, in vnworthineſſe, you muſt leaue that to the bleſſing
of Grace, whereon building the houſe of my hopes comfort, the foundation well
laide I the leſſe feare the fall of it: in the Subiect of mine Obiect can
be no Abiect, when <hi>Diana's Cupid</hi> knowes neither <hi>Vulcan</hi> nor
<hi>Venus:</hi> but if <hi>Pallas</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> make a coniunction
Copulatiue, in an Accident vnſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, the ioy may be vnſpeakeable: I
write not this out of the Arte, but the heart of loue, where there is more hope
of faith, then a poeticall fiction. To grow towards the matter, that I know you
moſt looke at, let it ſuffice you, that ſhortly I will ſée you,
and then acquaint you with that I hope ſhall not diſlike you, but to the
confirming of comfort, at the houre of conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in ioining hands vnto
hearts you will bee rather a father then a friend: in hope whereof, and prayer
for which, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt louing Nephew: <hi>T.
P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A diſcontentiue Letter vpon the deniall of
friendſhip.</head>
            <p>IF I were rich, I would be beholding to no beggers, and if wiſe,
I ſhould trouble no fooles: but he that is plagued for his ſinnes muſt
haue patience with his croſſes: yet ſpight of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, God will
bleſſe his Seruants: when Chriſtmas comes we ſhall haue Holy daies, and
though the Lent be long, Eaſter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes Good-Friday: I know to well you
vnderſtand mee to ill: but hauing knowne you to long, to finde that I doe in
you at laſt, meaning to trouble you no more, except with my fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
my will, I reſt as I haue reaſon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours as you mine. <hi>B. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:13"/>
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>HE is poore whom God hateth, and he rich that is contented: he is
wiſe that knowes himſelfe, and he vnwiſe that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtrueth an
other: puniſhments of ſinne are the trials of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and afflictions
well taken are the tokens of loue: twixt fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and faſting are daies of
indifference, and who wil not work muſt take the profit of idlenes. Your
knowledge to well may be taken to ill: but if your preſence may be
troubleſome, let me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat your abſence: ſo neither angry, nor well
pleaſed, till I heare better of your humor: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, as you mine. <hi>H. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter from a friend to a fantaſticall conceited
Madcap.</head>
            <p>IF I know where to finde you, I ſhould know how to ſend af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
you, for what I think of you, I ſhould know how to write vnto you, but I
thinke you are like a Bird, to flye vp and down, where you liſt, or like a
Cameleon, to change into all manner of colours: I am ſorie to ſee how your
vnſeaſoned braine ſets your wits a wool-gathering: but would you once be
your ſelfe, your friends would be glad of you, for there are good things in
you, howſoeuer you make vſe of them: If I had not heard of you now, I
thinke I ſhould neuer haue heard of you, for I could not deuiſe almoſt
what ſhould become of you, very ſtrangely you went from me, but if more
kindely, you would come to me, your welcom ſhould be in better then bare
words: &amp; therfore, if I may entreat you, and not to trouble you, when you
can conueniently, let mee ſee you, that wee may ſpeake of ſomething, that
is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be ſpoken off: bee you aſſured, I will not hurt you,
and what good I can doe you, you ſhall finde before I will tell you: and thus
with my hartie commendations to your<pb facs="tcp:21642:14"/>kinde acceptation, in hope
ſhortly to heare from you, and not long after to ſee you: till then and
euer, to the Lord of heauen I leaue you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured louing Friend. <hi>N.
W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwer.</head>
            <p>IF you were not eſtranged from that I left you, I ſhould know
how to finde you: but beeing as you are, I know not what to ſay vnto you: you
haue not heard from me a long time, and me thinkes to ſoone at laſt,
conſidering the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort I finde in your Commendations: For you would ſeeme
kinde, and yet in words ſhew the contrarie, when in the manner of your
writing, the bitter ouercomes the ſweet: if the good be marde, what ſhould
you doe with the euill: and if my wits be out of temper, what ſhould a foole
doe among wiſe men: I haue no Birds nor Beaſts to figure your fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but
an Ape is no man, though hee be nimble in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits: and hee that bites
like <hi>Diogenes,</hi> deſerues a name of his Nature, your hurt I feare not,
and your good I ſeeke not: but if I chance to come, neere you, it is a
chance, but I will ſee you, when as I finde my welcome, you ſhall enuie my
company: till then, rather to quite your courteſies, then to moue your
diſcontent, in the Anſwere of your Letter, loth to bee in your debt for an
humour: in more loue then idle talke, as I was and will be: till I ſee you,
and alwaies.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing friend. <hi>H. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:14"/>
            <head>A biting Letter to a Clamorous vngentlewoman.</head>
            <p>IF all Birds were Nightingales, the Owle would not make ſuch a
noiſe, whoſe feature is as ill fauoured as her Note is vnpleaſing: yet
ſuch deformed things are in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that perfection may be the better
eſteemed: her feede is moſt vpon vermine, except ſhee light on a Birde in
her ſleepe: when hauing filde her gorge ſhe fals to pruning of her fethers,
til ſhee leaue nere a good one on her backe: now if you vnderſtand not this
figure goe no further then your ſelfe, in whom being all that
vnworthineſſe that may deſerue all vnhappineſſe, in the ſame I
leaue you, as I found you, and ſo I reſt till I heare better of you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, as you ſee: <hi>W. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Anſwere.</head>
            <p>IF all Beaſts were Horſes, an Aſſe would not kéep
ſuch a braying: whoſe ſhape is as vnhandſome as his fleſh is
vnholeſome: yet ſuch creatures there are to ſerue the vſe of a Clowne,
onely to beare either burthens, or blowes: now if you vnderſtand not my
meaning, looke but vpon your pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and you ſhall ſee the proportion: in
which being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, worth any thing, in as little regard as may bee, till I
finde better cauſe of liking; I reſt as I was, and will be.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours as you may conceiue. <hi>A.
S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:15"/>
            <head>A diſcontentiue Letter of a coy Miſtris.</head>
            <p>YOur coy lookes condemne you for little noiſe, &amp; your
ſharp ſpéech of no ſwéet diſpoſition: it is pitie ſo
good apparell ſhould haue ſo ill lining, if I had not mine eyes I ſhould
wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip an Idol, but when it know coulours, I can geſſe which is in
graine to be ſhort, I will giue honor her right, and vertue her Grace, beauty
her praiſe, and wiſedome her honour, but where I finde conditions of a
contrarie Nature, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard them accordingly: the beſt is I am not the
firſt that hath been deceiue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> nor
ſhall bee the laſt that ſhall be deluded: and yet though this be no
excuſe for my folly, it ſhal be a warning to my diſcretion, in the
placing of my affection, in which not ouer bootes though ouer ſhooes, not
gone ſo farre but I can come home againe: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours if you were your owne. <hi>N.
R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Her Anſwer.</head>
            <p>IF you look for hearts in eyes, you may be out of the rule of
loue, and let me tell you that your crabbed writing ſhewes a crooked
diſpoſition, for your apparel and the lining, if I were acquainted with
your Tayler, I ſhould the better know the meaſure of your meaning: and yet
if I miſtake not your fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure it goes no further then your ſelfe, whoſe
out ſide is better then your inſide: if you deceiue your ſelfe, blame no
body but your ſelfe, and if you deceiue mee; I will ſnap vp mine owne
ſorrow: if you haue done amiſſe, know how to excuſe it, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it,
and when you finde a good warning, make your beſt vſe of it: In briefe,
howſoeuer you trouble your ſelfe, I pray you trouble me no more: for which
kindneſſe, I ſhall reſt in much thankefulneſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours as I finde cauſe. <hi>B.
T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:15"/>
            <head>A Letter written to a friend in time of great afliction.</head>
            <p>KInde <hi>Anthony,</hi> thou writeſt vnto me to know how I doe:
and though perhaps it may bee grieuous to thee to know it, yet being truth, to
thy loue I will tell it: if thou aſke how I fare? as hard as any man to liue,
if what I doe? ſhed teares for my ſinnes and pray for mercy, ſigh to
thinke of the follies of my youth, and ſorrow to ſee the miſery of mine
age: If how I paſſe my time? in the paſſions of the mind: if where I
liue, in the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of griefe, where
till I get into my graue, I thinke I ſhall neuer get out: if how I liue ſo
neere the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of death, as if one may liue dying, I dye liuing: for may I
not offend the heauens maieſty to ſpeake it, I think neuer courſe of life
came neerer to the thorny Crowne about <hi>Chriſts</hi> head which prickt him
round about: ſo is it with me; croſſes abroad and crucifyings at home, in
body and mind, puts pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to a high point: Oh my torments are innumerable
and almoſt intollerable, but that his goodnes that gaue me them, giues me
grace to beare them: for in briefe, if want to ſupply neceſſities,
vnnaturall kindred, vnfaithfull friends, vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable Creditors, vnquiet
neighbours and a moſt vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable wife, méet all together to the
tryall of a heart, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will hold or not, thinke if thou canſt, in
what perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity is my ſpirit: and pray in thy heart for my eaſe or end of
it: And thus aſſured, if thou canſt do me good, to find it, till I heare
from thee, and till death, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine what mine owne. <hi>W.
R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:16"/>
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>HOneſt <hi>Henry,</hi> I am ſorry in my heart for thy
heauines, and to eaſe thee of thy greefe could bee content to beare part of
thy paſſions: but let this comfort thee, that thou art not alone in thy
calamities; for euery man hath his croſſe, carry it as well as he can: and
for my ſelfe; though my ſhooes be finely made, yet they ſo wring my toes,
that they giue me many a twing at the heart: and yet I muſt commend my
Shoomaker and conceale my paine, becauſe the fault is in my feet: if wee had
not our ſinnes wee ſhould not haue our puniſhments: beleeue me
<hi>Henry,</hi> aflictions are the Badges of Gods bleſſings, if they bee
borne without murmurring at his will: hee that keepes a houſe may haue many
euill birdes about it, but I muſt confeſſe within doores the night Rauen
is the worſt, whoſe continuall croking is many times vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable: but
haue patience, it is a ſpirituall ſalue, that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all the ſores of
the heart, and a Tenure by which wee haue poſſeſſion of our Soules,
which guift of grace, God of his goodnes, in his mercy grant mee, and thee, and
all his ſeruants: deliuer vs from our miſeries and make the ioy of our
liues in the feeling of his loue: to which prayer, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thou wilt ſay
<hi>Amen,</hi> till I ſee thee, and alwayes: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine or not mine owne. <hi>R.
B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A kinde of quarrelſome Letter, vpon a frowne of a
friend.</head>
            <p>AT my laſt being in your company, your countenance gaue me
ſome immagination of your diſcontent: if you be angry, I would know with
whom, and for what: if it be<pb facs="tcp:21642:16"/>with your ſelfe, you know how to
mend your ſelfe, if with me, I know not why, nor care I wherefore; if it bee
your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I will not ſeeke to alter it, and if but your humor, I would
wiſh you to purge it, and ſo wiſhing you to ſatiſfie me, if you haue
any ſkill in Aſtronomy, whether wee ſhall haue faire weather or foule: as
I heare from you I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, as you mine. <hi>T. N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>MY occaſions of my countenance are ſecret to my ſelfe: at
which, if any take exceptions I wiſh me out of their company: your condition
I know not, nor deſire greater to bee acquainted with: for any hurt that is
done the amends may bee ſoone made; if you be deſirous of quarrels you may
haue your handes full of miſcheefe, but if you will be at peace with your
ſelfe, I know no man that meanes to trouble you, ſoe loath to bee at coſt
with any Almanacks, to looke into the rules of Aſtronomy, come what wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
will, welcome by the Grace of God: and ſoe I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours as you mine. <hi>D. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter to an Vnckle to borrow a horſe.</head>
            <p>MY good Vncle, I haue occaſion to trauell ſome few miles,
further then (I feare) my feet will eaſily carry me, if therefore I may
intreat you to lend me your horſe, for ſome few dayes, I will trauell him
eaſily, tend him carefully, and feed him ſufficiently: his ſafe returne
you ſhall not doubt,<pb facs="tcp:21642:17"/>nor my thankfulnes for your kindnes: ſo
loth to vſe needleſſe complements till I heere from you, and alwaies I
reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very louing Nephew. <hi>R.
T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>IF I ſhould lend you my horſe you might thinke me an aſſe
knowing your horſemanſhip, and his quality: but let this ſatiſfie you,
three thinges I will not lend, nor can I ſpare: my wife, my horſe, nor my
ſword: the one from my bed, the other from my ſtable, the third from my
ſide: the one for my pleaſure, the other for my defence, and the third for
my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: but, that you ſhall not think I will be altogether vnkind, I
haue ſent you heerein encloſed a piece of gold, to hire you a Nagge: ſo
hoping of your diſcretion, to haue patience with my deniall, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt louing Vnkle. <hi>T.
R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere. A Letter from an old man to his adopted Sonne,
going from the Vniuerſity to trauaile.</head>
            <p>MY good Sonne, I find by thy writing that thou art deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to
leaue the vniuerſity, and to looke abroad into the world; and being
perſwaded, that I haue ſeene ſomthing in it, deſireſt my counſaile
for thy carriage through it: to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie thy requeſt, let this ſuffice
thee in a few wordes, that I ſet thee downe for a caueat in all thy
courſes: if thou bee a Courtier, beware of coſt, if a Lawyer of
Conſcience, if a Marchant of Credit, if a Trades-man of craft, if a
Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<pb facs="tcp:21642:17"/>of error, if a Souldier of blood, if a Trauailer of thy
way, and whatſoeuer, of thy eſtate; and that the world may not ouergoe
thee, pray to God ſo to bleſſe thee, that his grace may euer guide thee,
and then haue thine eyes about thee, &amp; feare no hurt to come neere thee:
but for that all nations are not of one nature, nor all men of one mind, make
vſe of thy obſeruation, according to the place of thy paſſage: auoyd
groſſeneſſe, and niceneſſe, leaſt the one may proue as
diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious as the other diſpleaſing: cloy not thy ſelfe with friends
and purchaſe no foes: take héed of ſubtill wittes and ſmooth
tongues; for they are the cloſeſt pick-pockets in a common-wealth: take
heed of dead bones in nimble fingers, and haue no loue to play with painted
pappes, leaſt when you looke for your ſtake, you find a bare boord: ſort
with the beſt ſpirits, practiſe the beſt excerciſes, and loue the
beſt people: let God bee euer before thee, and his bleſſing bee euer with
thee: Soe, ready in any kindneſſe, to performe any thing that may doe thee
pleaſure, to the vttermoſt of my power, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy moſt louing father. <hi>D.
T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>MY good Father, touching your <hi>Compendium,</hi> for my
car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage through all courſes, how kindly I take it, you ſhall know when I
am able to requite it: in the meane time, I will make that vſe of it, that in
much thankfulnes ſhall make mee thinke of your kindnes: for I finde it like
<hi>Ramus</hi> his abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Logicke, where in a
little roome a man may run ouer a world: it is a little noſe gay, but full of
ſwéet flowers, and in the ſent I finde ſuch comfort, that I will
like, <hi>ſemper viuens,</hi> haue it euer freſh in my memory. While I liue
I will keepe it as the Apple of mine Eye, and if I liue to haue a Sonne, I will
learne it him as a<pb facs="tcp:21642:18"/>good Legacie: for my ſelfe I take it as a
portion of much loue, which while I liue I hope not to part with: In briefe not
to vſe ceremonious complements, with ſo iudicious an vnderſtanding in the
thankefull heart of an honeſt minde: till I ſee you, and alwaies: I
reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt louing Sonne. <hi>T.
W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of Counſell not to be preciſe.</head>
            <p>GEntle Coſen, I feare you are more full of conſcience then
wit: for if you follow your preciſe courſe, you will proue either a ſilly
Aſſe, or a holy Begger: for let mee tell you, while we are in the world, we
muſt vſe the world, and neither to wiſh to be out of it, nor to be idle
in it: bee not of the Family of Loue, without a working Faith, leaſt while
you looke vp to heauen, you be ſhut out of Gods houſe: to be religious I
allow you, and commend you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be
zealous, but in the muſique of the Soule goe not a Note aboue <hi>Ela,</hi>
leſt you be quite out of tune: and when your Braine ſwimmes in Humors, you
be drownd in the depth of errors: were you a Churchman, the commoditie of your
Altar, might giue you leiſure to contemplate: but beeing in an other
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament, you muſt looke about you in an other
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ature: In briefe, Gods prouidence
muſt be no excuſe for idleneſſe: you are commanded ſix daies to
labour, not onely with the mind, but all the members: heare then the word of
God, and doe thereafter: take h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed
of Hypocriſie, it is the high way to hell: from which God keep you, and leade
you in the way of Truth, that in the patience of your paines, you may ſee the
fruits of your labours: in which you ſhall beſt pleaſe God, profit your
ſelfe, and bee no charge to your<pb facs="tcp:21642:18"/>friends: So in my prayers for
you, hoping to heare well of you, to the tuition of the Almightie, I leaue
you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing Coſen. <hi>M. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Anſwere.</head>
            <p>MY good Coſen, I feare you haue more wit then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to
looke more into the world, then your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort aboue the world: wee are all Gods
Beggers, for who hath any thing that hee hath not receiued? and better I hold
it to bee a ſilly Aſſe, then a ſubtill Foxe, and a holy Begger, then a
helliſh liuer: you wiſh mee religious, and commend my zeale, and yet while
I am in the world I muſt bee a worldling: how greeth this together: wee
cannot ſerue God and Mammon: <hi>Martha</hi> was full of buſineſſe, but
one thing is neceſſarie, and <hi>Mary</hi> choſe the good part: I
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, want may be grieuous, and pouertie diſgratious in the world,
but the couetous GOD hateth: though I bee no Chaplin ſhall I not bee of the
Church? and in Gods houſe I hope wee loue all one an other: Now for the worke
of Faith, can the Spirit bee better exerciſed, then in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the word
of God? and when Meditation helpeth memorie, may not contemplation be
comfortable? Good Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen deceiue not your ſelfe, in miſdeeming of mee, be
you as farre from hereſie, as I am from hypocriſie, and if your Braine
ſwimme in the delight of Truth, you will neuer drowne in the depth of error:
To conclude, haue a charitable opinion of my diſpoſition, and I wil pray
for your perfection: ſo hoping on Gods prouidence, that I ſhall bee no
charge to your purſe: wiſhing you ſo cleere a ſight, that you may haue
a moſt happy ſéeing: in the true Loue of a kinſman, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, what mine owne. <hi>C.
B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:19"/>
            <head>A Letter from a Knight of great place, to a Gentleman to attend
him.</head>
            <p>HOneſt <hi>Henry,</hi> now I am come to the place that I haue
taken vpon mee, I haue many occaſions of employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of many ſeruants,
among whom I want one of that ſufficiencie that I know to bee in thy ſelfe,
whom I would willingly proferre to place of good profit: For know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thine
inſight into the world, how to manage buſineſſes, in their beſt
Natures, thou ſhouldeſt eaſe mee of much trouble, and bee a meane of
thine owne good. Strictneſſe of conſcience, may bee hurtfull in
curiouſneſſe; and ſecrecie, with ſufficiencie make a great proofe of
wit. In briefe, I know you can vnderſtand me, and therefore if you bee not
otherwiſe beſtowed, let mee know by your anſwere, how you like of my
offer: which howſoeuer ſhall not diſlike me, becauſe I know you loue
mee: So wiſhing you what you wiſh your ſelfe, till I heare from you, I
reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate friend: <hi>M.
I.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwer.</head>
            <p>VVOrthy Knight, I reioyce in your aduancement, and am aſſured
you can not want fit ſeruants for your employment, more worthy then my
ſelfe of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment: but in my humble loue giue mee leaue to tell you
the truth of my opinion: that there is nothing puts more home to the heart of
an honeſt minde, then to runne any courſe that may giue a wound to the
Conſcience: which while wit would excuſe, wiſedome layes open, when if
the<pb facs="tcp:21642:19"/>ſoule finde grace in Repentance of ſinne, the heart cannot
but bléed in the ſorrow of iniquitie: but God is all-ſufficient in
all things: and therefore knowing your vertuous diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to his
gracious protection leauing your moſt happie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, in prayer for
the ſame, with the encreaſe of all comfort, in the bounden dutie of my
loues ſeruice, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſeruant aſſured in what reſteth in my
power: <hi>I. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter to a Knight for the entertainment of a Steward into
his ſeruice.</head>
            <p>VVOrthy Knight; at my laſt beeing with you, you ſpake vnto mee
to doe my beſt in helping you to a Seruant, that you might employ for your
Steward: Now if it pleaſe you at my hands to accept the bearer hereof,
beleeue it you ſhall finde his ſufficiencie ſo fitting your content, that
I dare vndertake you ſhall not neede to ſeeke any further: I haue knowne
him long, and ſuch euery way his diſpoſition, as may deſerue good
regard in a very good vnderſtanding: he is honeſt, and wiſe, and able to
liue of his owne, yet in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your worthineſſe deſireth to follow
your fauour: for his Truth you ſhall not doubt it, and for his behauiour, I
know you will like it: for his wages I will leaue it to your wiſedome in his
deſart: ſo with his dutie commending my ſeruice to the command of your
kinde loue, till I ſée you, and alwaies: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very louing Kinſman. <hi>T.
R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:20"/>
            <head>A thankefull Letter vpon the tryall of his Seruant.</head>
            <p>MY good Coſen, among many courteſies, I thanke you moſt
kindely for my man, who in my great content, hath anſwered the Contents of
your Letter, for ſuch hath beene his carriage as hath gotten good will, not
onely of all my houſe, but of ſuch of my friends, as haue occaſion to
know his ſeruice: leſſe vice, and more matter worthy loue, haue I not
ſeene in a man of his ſort: yea ſuch hath beene his deſert of my loue,
as except for his better prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I will not part with him in haſt: For
in earneſt in many true Rules of Ciuilitie hee may be an example to good
Iudgements: In briefe, as I neuer found you to faile in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kinde care of my
good, ſo in this I haue great cauſe to thanke you: and wherein it may lye
in my power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite you, be aſſured you ſhall know I loue you: in
which, I reſt aſſuredly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate Kinſman and friend <hi>R.
S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of councell from a Brother to his Siſter vpon her
going from the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to the Court.</head>
            <p>SWeet Siſter, I heare thou art going from home to a high place,
from the countrey to the Court, beleeue it thou wilt finde it a place of
danger, for the preſeruation of thy beſt comfort: for there is honour both
to bee got, and loſt: but for a caueat in thy carriage, reade what I heere 
<pb facs="tcp:21642:20"/>haue written vnto thee, and lay it vp in thy memory, it will doe
thy vnderſtanding no hurt: Take heed of the Mewing of Muſke Cats for they
watch but for a Mouſe, and when they haue their prey, they are all gone away:
Let not the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding gloſſe of gay clothes dazzle the eyes of thy ſpirit,
nor faire tongues rob thee of thy fame: for a good name is not like a garment:
for if it once be broken, it will neuer bee ſet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe: there are
many hands that will bee plucking of flowers, whoſe hearts neuer care how the
ſtalkes grow, or wither: but if you will be your owne friend, let no man take
the fruit without the Tree: beleeue no idle vowes, nor vaine proteſtations,
for many times the tongue and the heart are farre aſunder: when the beſt
words haue not the beſt meanings: Nor let ambition bewitch thee, for the
ſinne is all one with the Lord or his Lackey: the Ice once crackt will crack
more, and what is the face that hath loſt the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the minde? ſweet
Siſter, I write not this that I feare thy imperfection, but to forewarne thee
from euill: And what good is to bee gotten, ſeeke it by that vertue that may
keepe thy colour without ſtaine, when a Maiden bluſh is the beauty of
modeſtie: ſerue God, and hee will bleſſe thee: pray to him, and hee
will defend thee? loue him, and hee will keep thee, that no hurt ſhall come
neere thee: bee conſtant in thy Religion, loyall in thy Allegeance,
courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in thy behauiour, and vertuous in thy loue, ſo no doubt but the
Court will grace thee, and the King of Kings will ſo aduance thee, that
though ſhe be no Lady on earth, thou ſhalt be an Angell in heauen: To which
happineſſe in prayer for thee, to his tuition I leaue thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy moſt louing Brother. <hi>D.
H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:21"/>
            <head>Her Anſwere.</head>
            <p>MY moſt louing Brother, I moſt kindely take your moſt louing
Letter, which I will lay vp for your ſake, and mine owne good, not in my
pocket nor my Cabinet, but in the inward Cheſt of my heart: and will dayly
reade it, as the rules of true wiſedomes direction: but to bee a little merry
with the anſwere of your figures, let Muſke Cats Meaw where they will, I
hope to bee no Venizon for Vermine, and for the Garden of my fauour there
ſhall no hand plucke aflower, except hee take the Roote and ſtalke to his
keeping: for the gloſſe of gay coates, they may bewitch Babies eyes, but
the eye of vertue, lookes after no vanitie, and for falſe hearts and faire
tongues, they are eaſily diſcerned, they goe ſo commonly together:
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt pride and baſeneſſe there is a carriage of ciuilitie, which I
hope to hit on without touch of diſhonour, ſo leauing Lords to their
Ladies, and their Lackeyes to lower Creatures, beſeeching the Almightie to
bleſſe mee heere with his Grace, and hereafter in Heauen to make the
leaſt of his Hand-maides rather then the greateſt Princeſſe on the
Earth with all the pleaſures of the world: to which prayer hoping you will
ſay <hi>Amen:</hi> in much thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe for the care of your
kindneſſe: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt louing Siſter. <hi>E.
B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:21"/>
            <head>A kinde Letter to a Schollar going from the Vniuerſitie to a
Benefice in a Citie.</head>
            <p>GOod Cozen, I vnderſtand by your Father, that you are determined
ſhortly to leaue the Vniuerſitie: but yet withall that you haue bent your
minde onely to the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Diuine vnderſtanding, and leauing the world,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take your ſelfe wholly to the Church, and in the Miniſterie of the word
to doe good vnto Gods people: I commend your determination, but with you, if I
might aduiſe you, to ſpend ſome few more yeeres in the Vniuerſitie, for
your further hearing and reading, for your better confirmation of your
reſolution: not that I feare the bleſſing of your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but that it is
a function of great charge, care, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Charge in regard of the Talent,
beeing out of the Treaſurie of Heauen, the riches of the Soule, then for care
in the wiſedome of the vſe of the ſame, to whom, at what time moſt
fitting for his Glorie that gaue it, and their good, that ſhall receiue it:
and for labour that you bee not found idle, when you ſhall bee called to
account to yeeld vp a rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning of your Stewardſhip: yet let mee not
diſſwade you from a good worke in reſpect of your young yeares: For
<hi>Iohn</hi> was the yongeſt of the Euangeliſts, and <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> was
yong in the Church of GOD; and therefore I feare not his gracious bleſſings
to thy proceedings: In hope whereof, and prayer for which, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt louing Vnkle. <hi>T.
W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:22"/>
            <head>A Letter to a worthy Knight beyond the Seaes.</head>
            <p>WOrthy Knight, I know you expect by this bearer to heare from me:
to write you newes into a forraine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I know not how my letters may bee
intercepted: and then if I ſhould write any thing either falſe, or
vnfitting, my hand would witnes againſt my will: and yet let me ſay thus
much of my obſeruation of the world, that in theſe latter times, I find
nature in ſo ſtrange a courſe, almoſt in the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of a world of
Creatures, that, had not the Creator of the earth a hand of mercy ouer it,
ſurely the ſinnes of the Creatures would call for a new deluge: but what
ſhall I ſay, my ſelfe beeing as a Cipher among figures, or a ſhadow
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, to ſee the world at ſuch a paſſe, as that I hold him happy
that is well out of it: but the beſt is, when night is paſt, that maſkers
will be gon, and when the Sunne ſends forth his beames, the Owle will not
dare to looke abroad: not to trouble you too long with little better then
trifles, giue me leaue only to Loue you, and to wiſh I were with you, which
if your returne be not the ſooner, may hap to bee ere you be aware: till
when, in the ſeruice of my heartes loue I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours aſſured at command. <hi>T.
N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>YOu dare not write vnto me in thee, ſparts for feare either of
your own miſtaking in your writing, or miſfortune in the deliuery of your
letters: but happe what will I haue written to you of the occurents of this
time, where betwixt<pb facs="tcp:21642:22"/>the Maſculine and Feminine Gender, a
coniunction copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue is of ſuch a force as puts downe all the ſpeaches
of the world, yea there is ſuch fluttering among theſe birdes, as if euery
day were Saint <hi>Valentines:</hi> and touching the wheele of the world, it
runnes ſuch a whirlegigge, that if nature mend not her courſe, ſhe will
be quite out of credit; in the Courts ſuch enuy, betwixt <hi>Mars</hi> and
<hi>Apollo,</hi> that a ſong ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time puts a ſeruice out of countenance:
in the Citty ſuch iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie betwixt <hi>Vulcan</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi>
that <hi>Mercury</hi> hath much to doe to ſaue <hi>Cupids</hi> bow and
arrowes: In briefe all the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of hell are ſo buſie in the world, that
if God did not bleſſe his ſeruants, the Diuell would haue a ſhrewd day:
but hee that is gratious hath not to doe with the vitious; and he that
truſteth in God, hath no feare of the Diuell: to bee briefe, if thy leaſure
will ſerue thee, make a ſteppe ouer to mee, thou ſhalt make thine owne
welcome, and thy charge ſhall bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: ſo longing to ſee thee?, till
I heare from thee, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine or not mine owne. <hi>R.
D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of Counſaile to a friend going to trauaile.</head>
            <p>GOod Coſen, I vnderſtand thou art determined to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, let
mee intreat thee to take heed to thy way: for mountaines are labourſome to
clime, and a valley may bee of a deadly length, woods may bee full of wild
beaſts, and the high wayes haue vnhappy holes; the Riuers may haue ſwift
ſtreames, the Seas are full of rockes and ſandes, and the beſt ſhippe
may haue a leake: learne therefore thy compaſſe before thou runne thy
courſe, leaſt if thou light among the Sirens, thou bee drownd ere thou
ſwim: Fortune helpeth the bold but ſeldome to a bleſſed end; and what a
wo is it to wit when<pb facs="tcp:21642:23"/>had I wiſt ſees the wheele, that threw him
headlong from his happineſſe: I ſpeake not this to diſanimat thee, for
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures are honourable, ſo the cauſe bee according, but if immagination
bee deceiued, how is diſcretion impaired? I would not yet like a Snaile haue
thee liue alway in a ſhell, but know thy way and then take thy walke: betwixt
<hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Charibdis</hi> the Channell is narrow, and hee that
lookes not with both his eyes, may be dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iued on one ſide: but what euer thou doeſt, do all to Gods
glory: Loue him aboue all, and feare nothing at all: but from him onely, haue
all that is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in all: ſo loath to make a long booke of a few
lines for thy inſtructions, let this ſuffice that I haue written: bee wary
in thy paſſage, and paſſe not wiſedome in thoſe limits: when thou
beginneſt to reade, in all the letters of the row the Holy Ghoſt bee thy
ſpeed: a little token of my loue I ſend thee, and ſo with my prayers for
thee, to the Lord of heauen I leaue thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull louing Kinſman. <hi>T.
N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>GOod Coſen your kind Letter I take moſt kindly, and let me
tell you what anſwere I make to your admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: no man knowes his way till
hee haue learned it, and hee that beſt knowes his compaſſe may yet run
his courſe awry, when ſodaine ſtormes may wrack the beſt ſhippe:
aduentures and labours are the paſſages of mans life, and mountaines and
vallies are the walkes of the world: hee that lookes to his feet need not feare
a hole in the way, and hee that feareth a beaſt is not fully a man: for the
riuers, ſtrong Oares will goe againſt ſwift ſtreames, and a cunning
Pilot will keepe the channell, where the paſſage is narrow, there is the
more need of heed, and if the ſhippe be tight, there is the leſſe feare 
<pb facs="tcp:21642:23"/>of her ſailing: for the ſongs of <hi>Sirens</hi> they are the
fictions of the Poets, but the figures are good warnings to beware the
miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheefe of wantonnes: hee that will winke when hee ſhould ſee, may
blame himſelfe for his blindnes, and yet the cleereſt eye may be deceiued
in a coulour: Immagination muſt breed hope, before happines bee attempted,
and where the intent is vertuous, the voyage is like to bee gratious: all is in
the will of God, vpon the hand of whoſe mercy, building the hope of my
comfort: aſſuring my ſelfe of your prayers for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of my
trauailes: till my returne and alwayes: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt louing Coſen. <hi>D.
T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter written to a Noble-man, by a Gentleman in
diſtreſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHen Lords begge of Kinges, I hold it the leſſe
baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to begge of Nobleneſſe: and though this booke begging be a
diſgrace to learning, yet ſince, <hi>Paupertas non est vitium,</hi> and,
<hi>Honos alit Artes,</hi> I hope your honor will rather releiue afliction then
rebuke preſumption: in the few lines that I héere humbly preſent
your honorable patience, I haue written that my heart is burſt,, and yet to
ſet it together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, what I cannot doe, if I ſhould dye in not doing of
it: vouchſafe my good Lord to read them, and me in them: &amp; with a few of
your golden Angells, deliuer me from a world of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate Deuills: which with
ſiluer daggers ſeeke to ſtab the heart of my liberty: which, beeing a
great part of my life, doe a Noble deed to ſaue it: God himſelfe will
requite you, and I ſhall bee bound to pray for you, that all the<pb facs="tcp:21642:24"/>good, that the heauens will, and the world can giue may befall you: So
hauing long knowne and euer loued your Honor, beſeeching the Almightie to
bleſſe the ſame, with encreaſe of aduancements, in the worthineſſe
of true Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, at the feete of your fauour, laying downe the
ſeruice of my hearts loue, crauing pardon for my preſumption, I humbly
reſt, during life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors: in all humble deuoted and bounden dutie
and ſeruice: <hi>W. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A pleaſant conceited Letter to a friend in the
Countrey.</head>
            <p>YOu write vnto mee for Newes, and mee thinkes it is Newes you
write vnto mee: For not hauing heard from you thus long, I wonder I haue heard
from you at laſt: And yet though I am merrie with your ſilence your Letter
is welcome, for I rather feared your health then your vnkindneſſe: but to
anſwere your expectation, let mee tell you that the occurents of this time
are ſuch as are either falſe, and then vnfit to write: or if true, not
worth the writing: onely this I dare tell you, that rich men play with the
world, and make a kinde of paradice vpon earth, while the portion of the poore
is moſt held in patience: For my ſelfe I am as you left mee, neither
beholding to friends, nor fearefull of enemies, and for the world I am ſo
farre in loue with it, that I could wiſh I were well out of it, and for your
ſelfe I wiſh rather your continuance of your home louing friends, then to
hunt heere after fortune a day after<pb facs="tcp:21642:24"/>the faire: To conclude, if I
come neere you, I will ſee you, where ſo euer you are I will loue, and ſo
to the Lord I leaue you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, what mine owne. <hi>N.
B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Anſwere.</head>
            <p>OLd wagge of the world, I ſee thou art neuer out of thy humour:
I am glad to heare from thee, not of thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents: but to ſee now thou
ſetſt them downe, which in a manner is as muſique, when I am ſometime
melancholy diſpoſed, but for the rich let them be proud only of their time,
for the poore may happen meet with them at their graues, and proue better men
in an other world: For thy ſelfe I held thy happineſſe greater in thy
Contemplation then many miſers in their large poſſeſſions: And in
briefe when thou art weary of the world come to me, and let vs talke of that
which all the world ſhall not heare of: ſo longing for thee, till I ſee
thee, or heare from thee, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, or not mine owne. <hi>B.
S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A kinde Letter to a friend in the Countrey, from the
Citie.</head>
            <p>KInde <hi>Anthony,</hi> I am ſure thou doeſt not maruell a
little at my long ſilence: I could make ſufficient excuſe, were it not to
tedious to write: But let this ſuffice, that a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled minde is not alwaies
in temper: and the world is at ſuch a paſſe, that the wiſe are amazed
at it, and for my ſelfe, ſuch I doe finde it, that as I can not get out of
it, ſo I ſcarce know what to doe in it: for wiſedome is watch't, whether 
<pb facs="tcp:21642:25"/>her workes bee like her faith, and folly is much in fauour,
becauſe ſhee pleaſeth the common people: ſo that I thinke I muſt
turne foole, if I will feed on fat meat: and yet it greeth ſo ill with the
nature of my ſpirit, that I had rather liue as a ſhadow among men, then bee
the ſubſtance of a monſter: oh my good <hi>Anthony</hi> how happy a life
doe you lead? that may heere the Birdes ſing in your woods, ſee your Ewes
ſuckle your Lambes in your fieldes, catch a fiſh with a worme, a Cony with
a Ferret, and a hare with your Greyhound, and by the way as you come home,
contemplate more comfort then the earth can giue you: for he that hath a heart
to lift vp his eyes, will bee of <hi>Senecaes</hi> opinion, that the mind of
that man is brought into a ſtreight, that can bee contented with earth: and
hee that were in his right wits would hold it the greateſt miſery in mans
life to deſire to liue, though in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: For mine owne part I wiſh I
were not out of it, but ſo in it, that I may not loue it: but I will neither
haſten my death nor prolong my life in this world, but attend his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
that will call me out of it; and the little time that I haue in it, I would I
could ſpend it in thy preſence, not to eaſe my charge, nor to charge
thee, but that in true worth, I know not a more worthy friend: and thus till I
ſee thee, which ſhal hee as ſoone as I can conueniently, in the affection
of an honeſt heart: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine or not mine owne. <hi>R.
B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>HOneſt <hi>Robin,</hi> thy ſilence was not ſo
diſcontentiue, as thy letter was comfortable, for thou writeſt not like the
world, bare words for matter, but alwayes like thy ſelfe, the fruites of true
iudgement: thou ſaieſt well of the world that it is a ſtrange paſſe,
when, let the wiſeſt heads haue the moſt<pb facs="tcp:21642:25"/>honeſt hearts, yet
will the eyes of wickednes, be prying into their procéedings, while
fooles craft is ſoone ſeene, when they moſt ſeeke to deceiue
themſelues: but let the fat Bulies of Baſhan, feed with <hi>Diues</hi> in
his delicates, pore <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> will haue a time to bee farre merrier
then meat can make them: Oh <hi>Robin</hi> the monſters of this age ſee not
their owne deformities, and better bee a ſhaddow among men, then ſo vumanly
a ſubſtance: while bleſſed bee the ſpirit, that hates the courſe of
iniquity: for my happines I confeſſe it is more then I am worthy of: but
moſt in contemplation aboue poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, when the Spirit aboue
Nature, ſees Grace aboue Reaſon, ſhewing it a better world then this
where it liues: yet while in this little time wee paſſe the pilgrimage of a
few dayes, more pleaſure is in the leaſt creature of life, then the
faireſt dead Idoll: if I catch a Trout with a flie, &amp; a Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingale with
a worme, the one ſerues me in my diſh, the other ſings in my Chamber, and
are not theſe comforts more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue, then to hang on friends, and hope of
fortunes, while the witts are dead weary, ere trauaile find comfort: well bee
the world what it will, come thou to mee when thou wilt: and command what thou
wilt, for though I ſay it, beleeue it thou haſt not a more louing friend,
that will approue it: ſo longing to ſo thee, that I may haue my fill of
diſcourſe with thee, with all the happines a heart can wiſh thee, to the
Lord of heauen I leaue thee: and ſo reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine what mine owne. <hi>W.
R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A melancholy diſcontentiue Letter, vpon a frowne of a
Kinſman.</head>
            <p>COſen, vppon your laſt lookes, I lookt a little into my
ſelfe, where I find it too true, that hee that is curſed in the cradle, can
hardly be bleſſed in the ſwaddell, and yet God is too ſtrong for the
Deuill, while Fortune is but the fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of fooles: Patience goes againſt
the heare with Nature<pb facs="tcp:21642:26"/>but yet where grace guides the Spirit the way
is not hard to heauen: the fore-horſe goes ſtraight, becauſe hee ſees
on either ſide, and the wilde gooſe raſe makes more haſt then good
ſpeed: I know there is a difference betwixt running and creeping: and yet who
is ſureſt footed may take a fall; excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are more ready then
foreſights, and yet the wiſeſt may be ouertaken ere he be aware: In
ſumme, he that cannot be him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, muſt be ſubiect to others
cenſures, and therefore to conclude with my croſſe, this ſhall be onely
my comfort: that hee that is at warres with the world ſhall haue peace in
Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; to which ioy after ſorrow God ſend mee, and all his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,
among whom hoping to finde your name in the booke of life: in more loue then I
found in your bookes, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing kinſman. <hi>B.
S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A diſcontentiue Letter of a Louer.</head>
            <p>WHen you were faire I loued you, for then you were not painted:
and when you were wiſe I honoured you, for then you were not inconſtant,
but when Art married Nature, and varietie ſhewed but vanitie, I was aggrieued
at my fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to haue grounded my affection on ſo little Grace; yet when I
ſee all true Birds haue fethers, I muſt let them take their flight: but yet
rather heare them in the woods then féed them in Cages: yet will I not
ſhut them out at my windowes nor hurt them, if they come in my houſe, but
regard them in their Natures: and ſo hoping that you vnderſtand the figure
in the honor of your beſt ſubſtance, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, more then you are your ſelfe. <hi>S.
T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:26"/>
            <head>Her Anſwere.</head>
            <p>GOod Coſen, doe not wrong affection with a falſe iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie:
Nature is euer her ſelfe, and I will bee no changeling: what my lookes were I
know not, but what my loue is you may know: Curſes and Croſſes differ
much in conſtruction, and puniſhments for ſinne are no plagues vnto
patience: God is euer good, and will help his ſeruants while the fictions of
fortune, are but the fruits of idleneſſe: Hee that builds his hope in
heauen, may the better carry his croſſes in the world, which bred in the
Cradle, will be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Saddle: And therefore my good Coſen, not
a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reioycing in the reſolution of your diſpoſition, command my
loue, though I cannot command my lookes: and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I am my ſelfe feare mee
not to be yours: for pouertie is no vice, where vertue deſerues honor: and
ſo wiſhing thee much good, and ready to doe thee any good, in the beſt
nature of good will: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very louing Kinſman. <hi>T.
R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Anſwer.</head>
            <p>VVHen you were wiſe I did eſteeme you, for then you were not
humorous, and when you were faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, I did loue you, for then you were not
iealous, but ſince imagination marde diſcretion, and iealouſie
ouer-topped loue, I will quit you with your owne Carde that I am ſory in my
affection to be ſo miſtaken in a friend: but ſince beaſts are moſt of
a hayre, though not all of a hewe, I will rather looke on them in a field then
leade them in my hands: and<pb facs="tcp:21642:27"/>yet will I not hunt them from my
ground: nor driue them from their field: and ſo hoping that your ſkill in
Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique will diſcerne a figure from a Cipher: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours ſo farre as I may be my ſelfe. <hi>M.
W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A comfortable Letter to a Kinſman vpon the Buriall of a yong
Sonne.</head>
            <p>SWeet Coſen, I know you are both religious and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and
therefore hope I ſhall need the leſſe reaſons to perſwade you to that
patience that may beſt make proofe of your diſpoſition: I am ſorie for
your ſorrow, and not your loſſe of your deare and worthy beloued little
Sonne: For know this hee was but lent you, till bee that hath him would ſend
for him: yea your ſelfe are not your own, but onely his that lets you haue
heere a being, till hee will haue you bee in a better place: Good Coſen I
knowe Nature is of great force, yet where Grace gouernes Reaſon, all is
referred to the will of God. I am aſſured that you pray day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that his
will may be done, and will you grieue that his will is done? Farre be it from
you: you know it is written, and I am aſſured you beléeue it, that
<hi>whoſoeuer loueth Father or Mother, or Wife, or Child more then God, is
not worthy of his loue:</hi> Take héed therefore not to offend the
Creator, with to much louing his Creature; and looſe not your ſelfe, in
looſing his loue, that you haue for his loue that you cannot haue: he is
among the Angels, and would you haue him among men? Yea, he is with God
himſelfe, and are not you glad that he is with him? Furthermore, if you were
alone in your griefe, you were the more to bee lamented, but when thouſands
are in your predicament let not paſſion exceed Reaſon, but humble your
will to the will of God, to whoſe heauenly protection, leauing your moſt
happy preſeruation: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt louing Kinſman. <hi>H.
B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:27"/>
            <head>The Anſwer.</head>
            <p>MY good Coſen, I thanke you for your kinde Letter, in which I
haue receiued no little comfort: but let mee tell you that a collop cut out of
the fleſh puts neere home to the heart, and therefore ſo farre as a man may
not offend God, giue me leaue to be my ſelfe, but yet I beſéech him
of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, I may not paſſe the limits of his loue: I reade that
<hi>Iacob</hi> ſorrowed, for the onely imagined death of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
and ſhal not I grieue to ſée my boy in his graue? and yet this is my
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, his yeeres were to yong to commit any actuall ſinne, and in the
election of loue I am aſſured he was a Lambe of the Lords flocke: it is
written, that GOD would haue yong Lambes for his Sacrifice, and my boy could
not be to good for his Altar: No, let not my ſoule liue, but in the ſeruice
of his loue: though I loued him on earth, yet would I not wiſh him from
heauen: for there is no Iewell ſo ſafely kept, as that which is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid vp in the Lords Treaſurie: I
haue read it, that ſorrow may tarry for a night, but ioy commeth in the
mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: then if the night bee long there is a time of mourning till morning,
and therefore blame not Nature in beeing her ſelfe, though the power of Grace
ſhall worke in her patience. In ſumme, I hope ſo to manage my affec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, as ſhall not imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ach my diſcretion, nor looſe his
loue that is the ioy of my life: to whoſe gracious bleſſing leauing our
eternall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, in prayer for that patience that may qualifie vnfitting
paſſion, in much thankefulneſſe for your carefull kindneſſe,
wiſhing with conueniencie to ſee you, and often to heare from you, in more
affection then proteſtation: I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very louing Coſen. <hi>T.
W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:28"/>
            <head>A Letter to an Hypocrite vpon betraying of a Friend.</head>
            <p>TO deny a Friend may bee a touch of vnkindneſſe, to deceiue a
Friend a proofe of ill Nature, but to betray a Friend to plaine a villanie:
Cheaters are ſet downe in the orders of euill perſons: Pandars are baſe
Raſcals, and the ſcum of the earth: but Traitors are moſt hatefull
villaines of the world: Among the twelue Apoſtles there was but one
<hi>Iudas,</hi> and wilt thou leaue the Saints to follow one Diuell? If thou
wilt runne his courſe thou maiſt runne to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: Wilt thou
miſtake GOD for Gold, and ſell thy Soule for a little Siluer? What will be
thy end? Shame on earth, and ſorrow endleſſe: What ſhall I ſay to
thee? but thinke what will become of thee, beeing a horrible Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, take
thy portion among them: Heauen will abhorre thee, and while the world hates
thee, hell ſtands gaping for thée: but GOD in his mercie, if it be his
holy will, forgiue thee: and ſo neuer meaning more to looke on thee, but to
giue all my friends warning of thee, to the will of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie: I leaue
thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy neuer more Friend. <hi>I.
S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>AN vnwilling offence may be an excuſe acceptable, what I ſpake
of a ſodaine, I repented at leaſure: for beleeue if no gaine could haue
made me ſo vngracious: but yet the occaſion of your diſcomfort, can not
but grieue mee in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſſe, though farre be it from my thought to doe
ſo<pb facs="tcp:21642:28"/>wilfull a wickedneſſe: be not therefore ſo bitter in
your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiue againſt my baſeneſſe: For if I were of <hi>Iudas</hi>
his Nature, I wiſh no other then his end: place me not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore among
Hypocrites, for I hate them in my heart, and deſire not to liue, to deſerue
that imputation: be you aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my griefe is greater for you then I will
ſhew, till in the fruit of my labour, I may make proofe of my Loue, wherein I
will not ceaſe till I haue effected ſomething to ſome iſſue in your
good, in which you ſhall ſee how farre it is from mee to bee ſo
vnhoneſt as I was vnhappy, and how farre my euill hap was from the Nature of
an euill minde: and ſo entreating your patience, ſo ſuſpend your
iudgement, I hope ere it be long to haue you write in an other humour: till
when beſeeching the Almightie to bleſſe you with health, and my heart
with happineſſe, to bee a meane of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: till then and alwaies I
reſt: howſoeuer you eſteem me, in the affection of an honeſt heart.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt faithfull friend. <hi>E.
B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of aduice to a friend that was to be married.</head>
            <p>FRiend <hi>William,</hi> I heare that you are ſhortly to take a
Wife, or rather to bee taken of a Wife: and that for a little times pleaſure
you will ſell your liues libertie: but if the matter bee not ſo farre gone
with you, let mee tell you a little of my minde, to make you looke about you:
for touching your choiſe, note what I ſay vnto you: if your wife 
<pb facs="tcp:21642:29"/>be to young ſhe knowes not how to make her ready, &amp; if too
old ſhee muſt haue one to helpe her out of her bed: if ſhee be faire,
ſhee will giue you cauſe of iealouſie, if foule, ſhe will bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance
to thee: if full of talke ſhee will bee troubleſome, if ſullen ſhee
will bee irkeſome, if of honorable Parents you muſt make courtſie to all
her kindred, if baſe you muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for a generation: If rich ſhe will
bee proud of her porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and he kept accordingly, if pore ſtill calling for
neceſſities and ſometime more then needes: if wiſe, ſhee will thinke
to gouerne thee, if fooliſh ſhe will diſgrace thee, if Barren ſhee will
be vncomfortable, if full of children ſhee wil be chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: if you truſt
her not with all you haue, ſhee will grow ſuſpicious of your loue to her,
if you truſt her with all you haue, ſhe wil make you a ſeruant to her: if
ſhe neuer loued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſhee wil not know how to loue you, and if ſhe haue
loued other, ſhe wil not leaue all for one: furthermore, if a man buy a
houſe, or land, he wil ſuruey it, ere he purchaſe it, and if he do not
like it when he hath it, he may find means to part with it: but for a wife hee
muſt take her at all aduentures, &amp; once had during life muſt neuer part
with her: and therefore if thou canſt fine a woman neither young nor old,
wiſe nor foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, ritch nor pore, kinde nor froward, honorable nor baſe,
talkattue nor ſullen, let me ſee her, that I may commend thy choyce in her,
but til then make ſtay of the Bells, they may not ring to thy Bridall: but if
thy affection bee ſetled and not to be remoued, then in Gods name, goe on
with Gods bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: So till I heare from thee how the world goes with
thee, wiſhing thee either a good wife or none: in my prayers for thy
proſperity, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine what his owne. <hi>B. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:29"/>
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>FRiend <hi>Samuell,</hi> your Caueats to my marriage I haue lookt
ouer very carefully, and am ſorry to ſee your courſe ſo farre ſhort
of ſuch comfort: for in the election of Grace, it is an holy ordinance of
God, for the good of his people: and in the world what companion can equall a
kind wife? If I were as nice in my choyce, as you are in your notes, I might
haue a long dreame, and awake find nothing: but come to your ſelfe, when you
dye what iſſue will you leaue of your loue? &amp; if you liue how vngodly
is your courſe? for my ſelfe I am fully reſolued rather to aduenture the
hope of vertue, then to runne a vainer courſe, and to nouriſh mine owne
family then to feed on another mans trencher: In briefe, when the Bells ring,
you ſhall know what buſines is at Church: and if you come to my houſe,
you ſhall be heartily welcome: till when wiſhing you as to my ſelfe, I
reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very louing friend. <hi>R.
T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of vnkindnes to a kinſman vppon a report of his
abuſe.</head>
            <p>COſen, I am ſorry to heare that I doe of you: how you haue
vſed me you know, how I can diſgeſt it you know not, I would willingly
forget vnkindnes, but if my patience nouriſh your preſumption, who
deſerueth to bee blamed if one folly beget another? you are my neere
kinſman, I would you were not ſo farre from me in kindneſſe, but I
feare the Prouerb proues to true in you, to vſe mee more like a kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
then a friend: but I can bee angry and not ſinne, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſorry and
not angry: for if you will come to mee, and acknowledging your fault make it a
warning to your fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<pb facs="tcp:21642:30"/>euill: the euill paſt ſhall not be
remembred, and the good to come not vnregarded: and ſo wiſhing to ſee
you, and the ſooner the better, till then I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing Coſen. <hi>D. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>MY good Coſen, were I not as neere vnto you in loue as in
Nature, I ſhould reuerence your yeeres, but ſcarce haue patience with your
humour, and indeede I ſhould take your vnkinde Letter as it is written: vpon
a falſe ſuppoſition to touch mee with an ill condition to wrong him at
all, whom I loue ſo much mee thinkes goes much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Note of good
Nature: For let mee tell you, I neuer vſed you ill, nor will vſe you but
well: and if any man haue otherwiſe reported, vpon his face, whoſoeuer,
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept your ſelfe, I will approue it: I thinke no man ſo diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt as
to deuiſe it, but if it bee a woman, though her wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe ſhew her
weakeneſſe, yet I wiſh her tongue had not ſuch ſtrength with your
eares as to put ſuch an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation into your heart, to bee ſo
needleſſe a trouble to your minde: to ſee you I feare not, and the
ſooner for mine owne ſatiſfaction, that where the fault is found it may
bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed: And ſo leauing to your diſcretion to conſider of my
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert: in irremoueable affection, I reſt: till I ſee you, and
alwaies.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured louing Kinſman. <hi>T.
W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:30"/>
            <head>A Letter of kindneſſe from a Gentleman to his loue, from
beyond Seas.</head>
            <p>SWéet Loue, how I grieue for thine abſence, thy
preſence when I ſée thée, ſhall make proofe: the Seas may
ſeparate bodies, but not minds; and there is no Nation in the world that can
alter the nature of loue: Miſtruſt not therefore my frailty; for, my
affection is fixed, and ſuſpect not mine infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, for my vow is euer
before me: if my buſineſſe were ouer, it ſhould not be long ere I would
be with thée: and bee perſwaded, ſo ſoone as I can I will
ſée thée: in the meane time, by this Bearer, a token of my loue
I haue ſent thee: by whom, I make no doubt, to heare happily from thee: ſo
praying for thy health, and our ioyfull méetings, till then, and
euer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, or not his owne. <hi>R.
B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Her Anſwer.</head>
            <p>SWéet heart, I haue receiued thy Letter louingly, thy loue
kindly, and thy token thankfully: beléeue it, if it might be no trouble
to thée, the Seas ſhould not kéepe me from thée: for,
whereſoeuer I am, my heart is with thée: of thy loue I am not iealous,
though I would be ioyfull of thy company: for me thinkes I liue, as a kind of
dead body without thée. By this Bearer, I returne thée a
requitall of thy kindneſſe, and wiſh my ſelfe had as ſwift a
paſſage to thy loue: In briefe, not knowing the trouble of thy
buſineſſe, I will only pray for thy health, till our méeting make
our happineſſe: and ſo reſt full of vnreſt, till I may reſt during
life, in moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full loue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine what mine owne: <hi>S.
P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:31"/>
            <head>A moſt kind Letter from a Lady to her Seruant of good
worth.</head>
            <p>MY ſecond ſelfe, whom if I could, I ſhould loue more then my
ſelfe, knowing thy Affection, and being aſſured of thy Faith, I wonder at
nothing more then, at what kéepes thée from me: I expected
thée long ſince, and haue now ſent to thée on purpoſe, to
know how thou doeſt, and why I doe not ſée thée: thou
knoweſt my Eſtate, yet am I poor without thee: for vnder heauen, I haue no
life but in thy loue: to which I hartily commend the hope of my worlds comfort:
let therefore, all excuſes laid aſide, thy preſence haſten my
happineſſe, and ſend me word by this Bearer, when I ſhall expect
thée whithout faile: till when, holding euery houre an yeare, my mind
being deſirous to bee diſburthened of ſome matter that I will not commit
to Paper: In hope of thy health, and prayer for thy happineſſe till I
ſée thée, and euer I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy louing Miſtreſſe, and moſt aſſured
Friend: <hi>M. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>His Anſwere.</head>
            <p>MY more then my ſelfe, moſt worthy beloued and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
Miſtris, I am ſorry for nothing, but that you ſhould be ſorry for any
thing: and eſpecially, that in me ſhould reſt the occaſion of your
diſcontent; but ſuch haue béene my bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, as haue ſo
croſt me in my comming, as when I haue had my foot in the ſtirrop, haue
brought mee backe from my horſe: but the heat is well ouer which hath
troubled my mind, that though I haue no diſeaſe, yet am I ſo much
diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<pb facs="tcp:21642:31"/>that finding my heart written ouer with the Letter
Y, and féeling ſmall comfort in the Vowell O, haue onely wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for
my health, to bee with the bleſſed Sillable V: Your Eſtate is your
ſelfe, vpon whom vnder heauen, is the ſtay of my happines: ſhortly I
intend to ſée you, and if your meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger make not the more
haſt, to bee with you before him, till when, and during life, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull louing Seruant: <hi>D.
T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21642:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
